<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A position against vainglorious, and that which is falsly called learned preaching</title>
            <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19926</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19926)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 990:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A position against vainglorious, and that which is falsly called learned preaching</title>
                  <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: H.I. [i.e. Henry Jacob].</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Against ostentation in preaching.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Preaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <p>A Poſition Againſt vainglorious, and that which is falſly called Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Preaching.</p>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>The Poſition.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N ordinarie Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vnto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Congregations to alleage Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether Philoſophers, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, or Divines; or to vſe Latin, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther languages beſides the vulgar, is vnprofitable, vnreaſonable, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is proved and confirmed by</hi> 7. <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the example of Chriſt is the beſt patterne for vs to follow in all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ordinary things, eſpecially in the
<pb facs="tcp:19926:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->works of our Miniſtery: yea if heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we willingly depart from this rule, doubtles we can not want ſinne.</p>
            <p>But their maner of Preaching who vſe Humane Authorities and Latin, &amp;c. is not like Chriſtes. For all men know Chriſtes whole courſe of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Iewes, how familiar and plaine, and yet how Divine &amp; ſound it was: even without all ſhew or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of ſuch lightnes, curioſitie, &amp; oſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as ſome now in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid allegations and manner of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching do vſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore thus ought all Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to do likewiſe; viz. after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt. And that other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of teaching (which ſome vſe) wanteth not ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Second: The Apoſtles example &amp; practiſe is like heerevnto. And as in
<pb facs="tcp:19926:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->other pointes, ſo even heerin doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les we ought to follow them, as we ſee that they follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But in that forenamed maner of teaching which ſome now vſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is their example and practiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. For all their ordinary Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Writing to the Churches was in great ſimplicitie, their wordes were all vulgar, their Authorities were all Canonicall: whiche the whole courſe of the Apoſtles <hi>Actes</hi> and <hi>Epistles</hi> doth teſtifie. And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth the ſame of himſelfe, ſaying:<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>I came not to you with excellency of wordes or of wiſedom, [but] ſhewing to you the testimony of God.</hi>
               <note n="ldquo" place="margin">vers. 4</note> 
               <hi>Neither [stood] my word and my preaching in the intiſing ſpeach of mans wiſdom.</hi> But this maner indeed he heere inſinuateth to have ben the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe and maner of the falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Some will ſay, that the Greeke or Hebrue propriety of ſpeach wil need ſometime to be waighed. And then doubtles the wordes are to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conſidered in the originall language.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, in handling controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies this ſometimes indeed is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But heere we ſpeak of <hi>Ordinary Preaching</hi> to Chriſtian Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In which, by thus doing this profitablenes very ſeldome appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, or rather truly never. For in ſuch ordinary places ſo exact diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of controverſies hath no vſe, as experience ſheweth vs. Eſpecially, that wee ſhould neede to vſe many wordes in a ſtrange tounge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If any ſay; Paul vſed ſometime Heathen authorities: as Act. 17.28. Tit. 1.12.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> We anſwere; He did ſo in deed:
<pb facs="tcp:19926:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->which yet nevertheles was but very ſeldom, even this twiſe only. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in all the multitude of his Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings and Writings that are extant, he never vſed any other Authorities then Canonicall. Which teacheth vs, how rarely and how vnwillingly in doctrine we are to vſe any other allegations, then ſuch as have in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abſolut Veritie. That to the <hi>Corinthians 15.33.</hi> (though it be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo written in <hi>Menander</hi> a Poet, yet) the Apoſtle citeth it only as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Proverbe, as a truth out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and vulgarly knowen: not as a teſtimonie from any Humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. 2. In thoſe two places before obiected he dealeth directly with the Heathens and Vnbeleevers; that if any thing would move them, they might be convinced by their owne Prophets. Wherefore theſe touch
<pb facs="tcp:19926:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->not our preſent queſtion which now we have in hand. For now our que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is onely concerning <hi>ordinary instruction to Christian Congregations.</hi> 3. He citeth theſe Poets in theſe 2. places in no other language then that only which was vulgar, and which the common ſort vnderſtood and knew right well. But with vs the common people vnderſtand not, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they admire and wonder at the deepe learning and incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knowledge of ſuch rare Doctors.</p>
            <p>Therefore it ſtill remaineth, that this curious and vain oſtentation of ſtrange tongues and Humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities ought to be ſhunned by all ſound and modeſt Preachers in their <hi>ordinarie teaching of Christians.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, the Apoſtles plainnes and ſimplicitie is to be alwayes followed and imbraced, which was their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant order and practiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
            <p>If God (as it were) debaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and would not ſpeak vnto vs in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> his Maieſtie as the Divine excellency of his word required that he ſhould, but choſe a familiar meanes to teach vs by even the Miniſtery of men, that is of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like vnto our ſelves: and all for this that our ſimple capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities might comprehend, and be comfortably inſtructed in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his will. Then ſurely in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought Men, who are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to imitate the Lorde heerein: viz. not to affect a profound, myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſtrange kinde of teaching, but to labour for wordes and matter eaſie and familiar to the capacities of the ſimpleſt.</p>
            <p>But thus<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 18 15,-19.</note> it pleaſed GOD (as it were) to abaſe himſelfe in the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of his people.</p>
            <p>Therefore, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Whatſoever is a ſtong induceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to make many to thinke that the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple worde of God without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Mens Authorities is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, nor the beſt meanes for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to ſalvation, that ſame is very ſcandalous and vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>But the alleaging of Fathers and Philoſophers, &amp;c. as beeing the beſt way of ordinary teaching, is a ſtrong inducement to make men think that the ſimple word of God is not a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient rule, nor the beſt meanes for doctrine to ſalvation. Which expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience proveth to much in a number of all ſortes of men.</p>
            <p>Therefore that vſe is very ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>When the hearers cannot proove <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> &amp; ſee whether the thinges which are
<pb facs="tcp:19926:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->Preached be ſo or no, then that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Preaching is bad and not to be vſed. For queſtionles in all ſound and profitable teaching that ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ought to be provided for, (which we ſee<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17-11.</note> the Apoſtle had care of) that the hearers may be able by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſearch and ſee whether that which they heare be ſo or no.</p>
            <p>But when ſtrange toungs are vſed, authorities and ſentences of Fathers and Philoſophers alleaged, then the ordinary hearers cannot prove and ſee whether thoſe things are ſo or no, which are ſaid.</p>
            <p>Therefore this order of Preaching is evill, and not to be vſed.</p>
            <p>That maner of teaching wherein <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> all that is ſaid may be vnderſtood by all, is better then that wherein many things vttered cannot be vnderſtood
<pb facs="tcp:19926:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->by all, but only by ſom who are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary and learned hearers.</p>
            <p>But when Fathers and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers &amp; ſtrange languages are vſed, many vnderſtand not that which yet they fooliſhly admire. Contrarily when the words are familiar and the matter Canonicall, then all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, both the learned and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and may receave edification.</p>
            <p>Therefore this way of teaching is the beſt, and the other the worſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, All the Ancient godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers themſelves (like as the later alſo) did preciſely keepe this maner of teaching, and altogeather ſhunned the other: namely Auguſtin, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, Nazianzen, Leo, &amp;c: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in their ordinary Sermons or Homilies which they made to the people.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19926:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 25 -->
            <p>Therefore in all reaſon it ſeemeth, the contrary vſe to ſpeake Latin to vs Engliſh, to cite Authorities of men in ordinary Preaching, is a great fault in Miniſters, and in no wiſe to be allowed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H.I.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>If any ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of God.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Pet. 4.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
